now entering that kind podcast network
[Music]
today's episode is brought to you by
kiki the easy safe and simple way to
protect your Bitcoin ether litecoin and
many other digital assets there's no
time like the present to protect
yourself from hackers malware and
viruses visit KP calm to order your
secure Hardware all today and use the
code humanist 10 for a limited time 10%
discount hello everybody
so before I start today's episode I just
wanted to do a life update so I've
joined the MIT Media labs digital
currency initiative as their head of
community and long-term societal impact
which I'm pretty excited about a really
nice group of blind people there so that
means that I'm gonna shut down my
patreon I've shut down my patreon and
that this podcast will likely continue
but possibly in a different form with
the Media Lab or with the DCI or
whatever so we'll see and I just another
quick note there my this podcast was
recorded before I joined the DCI so
clearly these are my views and do not
reflect those of the digital currency
initiative of the DCI so with that let's
get to today's episode and it's I
interview Danish Mactan burger today and
Daniel's done a lot of thinking about
these you know kind of complicated
complex macro systems that we live in
and that's just a quick I mean I don't
know if it's a warning it's also kind of
excitement Daniel and I really like
operating at these levels of abstraction
so that's where we got when we today
about one big topic which is a meta X
risk and so this is not only thinking
about kind of traditional and bi extras
I mean existential risk so this is not
traditional thing about like existential
risks like climate change nuclear
security biosecurity or AI alignment
instead it's asking a question what
actually creates those X risks what
creates those existential risks and you
can think of this as something like two
kinds of processes where we've had
evolution as a process and evolution was
a generally a nice process that um thank
you evolution for creating me evolution
had micro rivalry but created macro anti
fragility right so the like the earth as
a entity that was a
a blossoming anti fragile symbiotic
nature thing but we've humans have
created this new process as a result of
abstraction and design and technology
and science and this kind of process it
creates it has micro rivalry in the
sense of like market competition but it
doesn't have macro antifragility right
we don't have if you look at the world
today or something like the Industrial
Revolution Industrial Revolution was
created by a process and that process
doesn't have a built into that process
is not something that says hey let's
internalize our externalities or
you know let's close these loops and
instead we get something like climate
change and so these this process tack is
a process gives us these multipolar
traps with this exponential tech that
will produce these exponentially harmful
externalities eventually and so that's
the world that we live in and we need to
switch away we essentially need to
create a new kind of process design a
new kind of process that kind of takes
the best of both worlds here where we
have where we create macro
anti-fertility but it's not created as
an emergent process of evolution and the
micro rivalry but instead is actually
kind of by design by by us as humans so
that's primarily what we talk about
today and just as a quick note you know
we put a lot of context before this so
it's definitely juicy in the first 30
minutes but it gets especially juicy in
the last 30 minutes or we go deep on
this
so with that hope you enjoy the episode
[Music]
hello everybody my name is Rhys landmark
and you're listening to another episode
of creating a humanist blockchain future
in this podcast we take a systems
thinking approach to doing good in the
world we have a couple different series
to focus on different system scopes and
today we're focusing on series a macro
systems where he asked the question
where are we as humanity headed and to
dive into that question I'm very happy
to introduce Danish Mactan Berger to
this show Daniel loves exploring various
topics of civilizational significance
trying to shake them for good and he's
one of the best systems vocal processors
I know and much of my own thinking has
been shaped by him so Daniel thanks for
being on the show and welcome my friend
me too okay so we're really gonna push
the question where are we as humanity
headed today and let's gonna start at
the top here and before talking kind of
too deeply about our current context or
what's happening Daniel how do you think
about kind of goals like what do you
think about goals for our civilization
or when you're trying to like you know
optimize for a metric or something like
that what are your big goals mm-hmm so
before talking about what I think good
goals would be I think the question
you're actually asking about is is a
goal-oriented framework actually a
adequate or good framework or they're
other frameworks we want to take and so
obviously Western culture has been and
particularly industrial post scientific
technological and even computational
culture has been very oriented to goals
kind of process and we can attribute
both lots of successes and most of the
failures of the world or many of the
failures of the world to that process
because if I define a goal and it
doesn't include everything that will be
affected by the nature of what I do to
get there then whatever is affected that
I didn't define as part of my goal as
the space where externalities can happen
and even in the you know very
well-intentioned nonprofit you know
whatever kinds of sectors we see all the
time having things like okay so we have
a goal to end extreme poverty and
childhood hunger globally or within a
particular area that seems like a pretty
awesome goal as well she's ever seen the
child who's hungry or
mother watching her child be hungry the
tricky thing is if my only goal is to
end hunger I can do it through Unruh
noble agricultural methods that dump
nitrogen into the river deltas removing
dead zones in the ocean even faster
moving us towards actually extinction as
a species and collapse of the biosphere
writ large which is okay so we prevented
some people from dying over the very
short term and made it more likely that
everyone dies with medium term yeah so
at minimum when we think about goals we
could at least just start by this hand
waving kind of thing of saying our goal
is X whatever X is right stop extreme
poverty and just add this little caveat
which is our goal is to do that and not
externalize harm to anything else that
matters and now when you start exploring
how do I know what else might be
affected that could have harm
externalize that isn't obvious in very
complex systems and with technology that
has lots of different causal dynamics
that are associated and then the
question of what are other things that
matter and what is my ethical and
existential framework for assessing that
then you start to realize that that kind
of hand wave leads it way to a much
deeper process of what we might call
omni consideration yeah let me pause you
for a second actually there because I
think that there's a lot of good juicy
stuff a as you said we're kind of so
used to thinking of this goal framework
and it's almost it's hard to get out of
it in some ways and like you say I super
girth you say once we create a goal
whatever that goal is X and you also say
what are all the externalities of X and
how can we make sure that we're you know
minimizing the negative externalities
and upping the positive externalities of
that X is there I guess to go a little
bit deeper on that this kind of goals
perspective and you kind of start to
allude to the stomach's is like there
are there are people in the world so I
would say I'm like a relative kind of
effective altruism list in terms of I
agree with you know generally agree with
like consequentialism and kind of
outcome-focused ends focused mindsets
those are all kind of goal they have
kind of goals as a part of them so how
do you think about something like
effective altruism as kind of a mostly a
goal focused or kind of an outcome
focused mindset is that going to be is
that good for shaping the world
positively effective altruism is a
valuable step in the consideration
process of saying if we really care
about having actions that have a
positive impact on life at large how do
we go about influencing our choice
making basis of what will be effective
and how can we use very effective tools
like rationality to inform better choice
so insofar as it's asking what are the
right epistemic frameworks to inform
good choice that's a great step now of
course I'm going to say that it is a
limited step and the limits are actually
fatal and the direction and permeate
rates have to happen so here's a couple
examples when we talk about the limits
of goals because the goal is always
embedded within a larger context and so
you have to factor it's in the embedding
functions and that's where the topic of
externality comes and how even think
through externality we're mostly only
going to forecast within domains that we
already know a lot so as we're getting
into exponential technology where there
are faster rates of change more
complicated more complex systems etc
then there's more stuff that's going to
happen that we don't forecast well and
faster coupling from the micro context
to the macro context it used to be that
whatever happened in a microwave wasn't
going to affect the biosphere or human
civilization at large because stone
tools just don't have as big a
consequence as AI or nanotech biotech do
and so because of the larger scale and
faster timeline coupling coefficients of
micro action to macro dynamics
externality is that much bigger of a
topic right and it's an exponentially
bigger topic so let's just take small
cases and didn't look at what happens
when you put that on an exponential
curve
so say we take medicine because in
medicine we're talking about what is
health and but in a body that's a
complex system but we take a complicated
approach of trying to define health in
terms of a finite number of metrics so
we're going to look at your low density
lipoprotein and your high density
lipoprotein and a couple different
cholesterol metrics and blood pressure
and blood sugar and whatever in and as
time goes on we look at more and more
metrics but then the idea is that there
is a range in which we want to see those
metrics and so then the goal is at first
we can just say okay your cholesterol is
too high our goal is to lower
cholesterol that seems like a reasonable
thing if I have a reason to think that
high cholesterol increases the
probability for certain diseases but now
I have to dig a little bit deeper in
this first step is obvious the second
step is more important the first step
says okay when I say cholesterol is high
so I want to lower it giving a statin
drug actually works it makes sense I'm
gonna lower low-density lipoprotein I
did not ask why the cholesterol was high
in the first place is that possibly a
protective mechanism to the arterial
system from some type of oxidative
damage or toxicological damage or
whatever that that's arising from is
that a sign of other systems homeo
dynamic systems being out of balance
we're just addressing that symptom means
underlying other patho ideology will
continue is there a side effect on
metrics other than LDL and maybe ones
that we haven't even measured and done
longer-term analysis on of the method
that we're using etc so then we can say
well the statin works for that but not
how the system is more dependent on it
its own ability rated cholesterol is
less good why it was off we still don't
know and the side effects of the statin
might be things like liver toxicity
brain toxicities and we say okay well
that's not the best method but that is
still our method right that's how we do
medicine and that's why if you think
about medicine we have really amazing
acute medicine and really terrible
chronic medicine so in acute medicine
meaning if we know the acute onset of
the illness like you just got shot and
the problem is a bullet that went in we
can take the bullet out sew it up and
there isn't deeper underline more
complex causation
pretty straightforward and we're really
good at that you just got an acute
infection you just got an acute
poisoning we can deal with those things
pretty well but when we talk about
psychiatric disease or autoimmune
disease or neurodegenerative disease or
cancer or anything that doesn't have one
obvious immediate cause you'll notice
that for the most part we don't have
anything that actually looks like a real
cure or prevention we have symptomatic
treatment and we might have things at
slow rates of progression and the reason
we don't and so you can't there's a
classic example we can cut it a cancer
that we can radiate it out we can poison
to help but we're not that good at
saying why is it growing in a way that
it wasn't when the person was younger
and that it doesn't and other people and
how do we actually address that because
it doesn't have one cause it has a whole
bunch of different causes and they're
not even the same set of causes in
different people so now we have to
actually not do a generalized bell curve
approach but do a let's understand this
complex system uniquely factoring
multifactorial causation delayed
causation causal Cascades should that we
are epistemic Limon that good at we do
the same thing for the world when we're
saying we want to feed kids in this area
and we're not saying what is wrong with
the macroeconomy that actually creates
poverty and what you know etc like what
are the actual causes of this problem
and then of a particular solution that
we're going to come up with it doesn't
address the causal dynamics well what
are the side effects of that solution
going to be is this Hagrid cultural
method going to lead to more nitrogen
runoff leading to larger dead zones in
the ocean that is actually worse for
everyone long term and writ large and so
what we find is then we look at the LDL
and say okay so we want to look at LDL
and these liver enzymes and a few other
things and then we try and put more
metrics and run optimization on those
metrics which didn't we say big data and
and machine learning will help us do but
this is the kind of the key thing no
matter how many metrics there's a couple
things here when we say that goals are
limited we also are saying that
optimization theory is limited
for a couple critical reasons so now I
go from two metrics to 200 or 2000
metrics but there's still other things
that are happening that are outside of
the metrics that I'm seeking to optimize
that are mostly in either the beyond
factorable within this model or the
actual unknown unknowns but that might
be critical to the whole system and so
when I'm running optimization on these
end metrics
I'm also affecting a lot of other stuff
that I'm not paying attention to
optimize which is this places where I'll
probably externalize harm is I'm driving
a system where all those things are
interconnected without actually
acknowledging they're in the correct and
infected in other words our model of a
complex system is not how the complex
system actually works so when we treat
the actual reality as the model and we
try and optimize for the model the place
in which the reality is not the model
gets up and so when you define a
complex system as something that has an
emergent property beyond how you model
it when you model it you get certain
system dynamics awesome complicated
system complex system is the predicted
dynamics of the model don't explain all
of the dynamics then you have to say
it's very different epistemology other
than n-dimensional metrics an
optimization theory to account for what
is actually going on so pause for a
second so I agree with a lot of that and
I want to talk about this sec but so you
talked about the I agree there's a bad
forecasting piece or we live in this
world where we have Black Swan style
events and over hyper interconnected
lots of power dynamics of external or
lots of sorry Exponential's happening
and when all that happens if we set our
goals and then don't account for the
externalities or actions then the sad
externalities can turn out to be really
big because everything's so
interconnected and powerful now and I
agree with what you're saying when you
think about any of these actions and
this gets into how kind of to think
about this stuff is like when you think
about taking an action before you do it
think hey why is there this problem in
the first place to try to go to that
root cause level and then B what are the
externalities of that action
so in this final piece which you're
getting to here's this map is not the
territory thing here and it's especially
true for complex systems and so I just
kind of want to recap
that's tougher listener and then have
you go and say okay so if we can't use
this if I can't just keep adding metrics
to MySpace
is there an AK what is the new
epistemology that I should be thinking
about that will actually allow me to
allow us to to succeed in this new world
right so I want to share another
framework that will help the
consideration here and this is not a
happy thought at first but it's a
necessary thought which leads us to be
more effective in considering how to
have happy thoughts around this so it is
that it is a lot easier to break
than it is to actually protect or build
stuff and there is a entropic preference
that we have to consider and just to
have a very simple kind of prima facie
of that the house that I'm in probably
took a year to build and the record ball
can take it down in minutes and if you
think about an old-growth forest and the
thousands of years it takes to get the
biodiversity and complexity of that
forest and how long it takes with a fire
or a d9 that take it down you really get
a sense of the orders of magnitude of
the timelines for construction versus
destruction of complicated or complex
systems and everything from from things
like that how long does it take to build
a globalized infrastructure and how
quickly could we actually break it all
the way to how long does it take to
build trust and how easy is it to break
it and so when you factor that you
realize that there's a couple orders of
magnitude more ways to break stuff than
to build it in faster time processes on
that so when I'm factoring externalities
and I'm thinking about some new
technological capacity and I don't
understand actually forecast the
possible externalities well because I
don't even know that space I'm opening
up a new epistemic space with new types
of causal dynamics and feedback loops
and couplings that are very hard to
think about and there's an orientation
that there will be more total ways of
having destructive effects than
constructive and that they will be
faster this is something we have to
consider very deeply and when you can
imagine
when we first got stone tools down we
killed a lot of things faster than we
ever had before and we started the
beginning process of species extinction
human induced species extinction when we
first started kind of figuring out fire
we burned a lot of down before we
got good at containing fire but when you
move up to AI and nanotech and biotech
and things that are pattern replicating
Tec meaning that the failure of the
thing is not just that it caused a
problem but that it causes a cascading
problem that once initiated might not be
stoppable you really have to change the
epistemic framework of good things are
mostly good progress at all costs
history is written by the winners we
kind of ignore the ugly parts and let's
keep pushing and focusing on the good
side of technology for some very limited
definition of good because the
destructive applications at that scale
are large enough to actually destroy the
entire playing field where the positive
applications just don't actually get to
matter anymore
so there's an increasing kind of AD
exponential scale Oh exponential
constructive and destructive forces both
the destructive forces become larger
than the playing field can handle in the
game in so with exponential tech you
either figure out how to prevent and
internalize externalities or the game
eventually self self terminates and
though the type of process that we've
used for all of history until now is
itself self terminating yep so could I
you policy for saying they're saying
that's a lot of juicy stuff there I'm
reminded of two leaves and an ear bar
Yama's precautionary principle here
which is the idea that even if something
has you think it's gonna be really good
with a 99% chance of being really good
but it has a very very small percentage
chance of like actual ruin or like
existential risk then it's like well
then you shouldn't do it you know and
when we live in this world where
everything is interconnected and where
everything is becoming more powerful
than that that lose side that
destructive side can become yet becomes
we have to change kind of our way is
given our exponential tech so let me
you follow up on that for a quick second
here which is if we're trying to change
our ways here and we're trying to be
kind of taken all the externalities into
account how yeah how can we begin to
start to do that mm-hmm so great
question again I'll say one other thing
that I think read some of the context
great one of the important things to
consider when we think about the topic
of negative externalities that so one
thing we just said is the kind of
entropic gradient right so we have to
factor that another key thing is the
topic of weaponization if I create a new
technology and it is the capacity to
affect change through the causal lever
on choice right and I'm gonna make a
choice my technological understanding of
some mechanism allowed me to make a
technology that's a big lever on my
choice so my choice has bigger effect
then did before well that same
technological capacity can be a lever on
lots of kinds of choices right and so
one of the things we have to understand
is that the moment we actually deploy a
type of asymmetric technology then it
gets reverse engineered iterated upon
and utilized for all purposes that are
incentivized by all agents and so I had
just had some guys talk with me the
other day about an AI project they were
working on of how they could use some AI
information technology that was novel
they just developed to get out some type
of what they thought were positive
political agendas to solve some current
near-term problems and I'm like and you
don't think that the other side's that
have as much incentive and pretty good
Intel will pay attention to the new
technology you have reverse engineering
and utilize it for the other purposes
and simply and the and they thought
about me like like I guess that will
happen and I said now take all of the
sides in this multi agent dynamic that
all have rival risks incentive to
weaponize the technology against each
other for their agendas and all you do
is up the ante of the playing field and
so nukes didn't actually make us safer
like they made a safer but we actually
have increased risk of existential risk
from nuclear warfare relative to a world
that had just never developed nukes okay
and so this is the multipolar trap where
each agent doing the thing that seems
like it provides and whether the agent
is a person or a country or a company or
whatever each agent doing the thing that
seems like it's best for what they care
about in the near-term actually leads to
a system disposition that is worse for
the system as a whole over the long term
and this is what we call a multipolar
track or a race to the bottom right a
tragedy of the Commons and arms race are
all examples of this and with
exponential tech we have an exponential
race to the bottom type scenario so one
thing can say is in terms of goals or
necessary criteria of system design time
constraints is that we have to solve not
just for some multipolar tribe but
categorically for the class of
multipolar traps as long as you have a
rival risk incentive to utilize
technology in a way that will directly
or indirectly cause harm you have a
near-term incentive to do that and you
have exponential tech and anytime anyone
deploys that everyone will be using it
for rivals purposes we we are actually
completely yep yep so can i pause
you for a second there on that great and
so i agree with this and this is in
something that you call like the
generator functions of x risk and these
are these these multipolar traps and you
can look at it when you think about the
existential risks that exist today there
are things like nuclear security and
that's an arms race it's like you know
couldn't we have stopped at like I mean
maybe like three nukes or something but
now we have thousands of nukes and you
think about biotech again it's like
people doing things there in these
win-lose game dynamics where if they
stop and if they don't if they don't go
quicker and same with like artificial
intelligence alignment it's like ooh
maybe Google and Baidu and the you know
Chinese government's new whoever are
going to be nice around and be and try
to be safe but actually they're gonna be
in this win lose game dynamic where if
they're the first ones to get AGI then
they will have lots of rewards and so
there's a disincentive to kind of chill
and wait for the safety things and
something like climate change obviously
is a an example of the that's like a
perfect example the tragedy the Commons
where you have
it didn't matter that much at the
beginning when we started the Industrial
Revolution that we were pushing stuff
into the atmosphere but as you say
once it gets exponential then and we
ignore that externality then we're in
one of these multiple traps or no one's
caring about the earth and then
everybody gets screwed up so I agree
with all that I also agree with you and
saying this weaponization piece is a
very interesting one it's and it takes
it's weird mindset that we talked about
a little bit before with this weird kind
of Omni considerate mindset where you
have to kind of this is both powerful
from an individual perspective we tried
like a steel man the other person but
it's also very powerful from this kind
of systems perspective we say hey if I
do something and well maybe it's good
for me but what happens if everybody
does that you know then is it still good
and is the thing that I'm using the tool
and I just did a podcast on new power
these kinds of new power are those tools
and those kinds of powerful things how
are they going to be used by
quote-unquote the other side you need to
think about that in terms of this
weaponization piece um so I agree with
all of you here one thing that I might
be worried about just as a heads up is
like this to some extent I think that
people might get stuck in a trap right
now which is where I'll make maybe like
a postmodernist trap where it's like you
we had been in the the world of
modernism we were excited by the world
we said hey we're gonna be nationalists
we're gonna go go go and then
post-modernism came around and we
rejected those myths we said no nothing
can be real and like everything is kind
of kind of gradients or whatever and it
feels like it may be a similar thing
here where you're like you say like oh
man Reese we need to think about all the
externalities all the time or like how
many consideration all time or like how
can we how can we then make choices if
we have to be worried about the
externalities kind of of everything yeah
great question and as you can guess and
what I'm going to advocate is an
adequate at the seeming and ethical
framework is not post-modernism nice a
couple more parts that we need to
construct in here is so one thing
regarding weaponization and just a very
simple practical thought for people who
are wanting to do good I was having this
conversation with Tom Chi the other day
and you know he's a really brilliant
prototyper inventor robot assess
technologists working on good things for
the world and we were talking about this
problem of organisation and cognizant of
that his approach and I think this is a
approach that Bucky fuller laid out very
clearly and and others have is let's
take technology that already exists for
weaponized purposes and start to
popularize how to use it for actually
positive purposes so we're not
increasing the technological power
landscape we're repurposing the shitty
power to better power and so we aren't
actually going to be driving a
multipolar trapping race to the bottom
we are within the current landscape of
not having solved from multipolar traps
categorically yet we're at least driving
a race to the top and I think this is a
really key idea so when he's looking at
how do we take drone tech that already
exists for military purposes and sucks
we're not gonna make fundamentally
better weapon izybelle drone tech but
we're going to use it to plant a bunch
of trees to pull a bunch of co2 out and
stabilize topsoil and other things you
have a much lower risk of weaponization
in that approach and so I just want to
offer that as one very simple kind of
strategy that people can think about now
that still doesn't mean that a
particular approach won't have
externalities and doesn't think thought
about of course if I take a desertified
area unplanned trees for the goal of
sequester co2 and so I take whatever
genetically engineered plants the
Questor co2 the fastest and just plant a
ton of it I might get all kinds of
ecological problems as a result of
anything from mono cropping to invasive
species to whatever else right so I
still have to think about complexity but
I don't think about weaponization
increasing the potential of the power
landscape as much so that's one
consideration next I want to go onto
something about multi polar traps but do
you want to say anything on that purpose
oh no no no you go to multiple traps
thank you for checking them so for
people who aren't familiar with this
topic well yet there's a article on
Slate star codex
meditations on Moloch articles on that
whole site I think and one of the better
introductions the concept of multiple
chunks I will share and whether we get
to it on this podcast or another time a
different set of insights about a
categorical solution to multipolar traps
but just so that people understand them
a little bit and why they are so hard to
get out of if we you mentioned a couple
examples but I want to highlight the
system dynamics a little bit more
explicitly because as you said this is
actually not the source of one X risk
this is a generator function for all X
risks because one things about it and so
if we don't resolve it categorically
then we just kind of move the timescales
a tiny bit so let's take a tragedy of
the Commons it started a long time ago
and we just say okay we got a number of
tribes that are all seeking to increase
their own well-being they are in an
implicit competition with each other for
the same scarce resources at a certain
point that implicit competition economic
resource extraction wise can become so
problematic that they move into an
explicit militaristic competition which
we can see how it happened but let's
just even start to take first okay I
don't want to cut all the trees down
because I actually really like the
forest I have a whole spirituality about
our connection with nature and we need
the force to live because that's where
the animals live that we hunt and etc
and I actually don't need that many
trees I just need a few trees some only
in cut down those few trees except the
population of these other tribes and the
total number of tribes has been
increasing and they're all cutting down
trees and so I know that if I don't cut
down the trees it still doesn't ensure
that there's a forest because the other
guys didn't cut down the trees so
there's not gonna be a forest anyways
but he's actually my competitor because
he's going to use those for weapons
weapon making that if I don't also do so
he will actually end up killing my
people or people be able to outlive us
through a famine because of total amount
of economic accumulation or whatever it
is so since I can't actually keep the
forest because of those guys and even if
I tried to make a truce with this one
tribe there's this other tribe that we
just can't even talk to
so if anybody does the up thing
of cutting down a bunch of trees then we
are in a race to all get them first to
keep the other guy from having them
because there is no incentive and
leaving them and because then it's best
for us to have them so now we could have
done a lot more trees than we need and
so but they only do that because they're
thinking the same thing about us where
the up other tribe to them right
and so now we all realize that we have
to increase how good our axes and saws
are and how many people are cutting down
forests to cut it down faster because
we're all racing to get that wood or the
pigs or the whales or the farmland or
whatever a dead trade and so now we are
not just destroying the world upon which
we depend we are in a race to destroy it
as fast as possible and if we don't we
assume it will still get destroyed and
it will be worse for us and we have no
chance of winning right so this is a
scenario where anyone does the up
thing and it sets a precedent for
everyone else to actually be better off
near-term if they do the up thing
even though it leads to everyone being
worse off over the long term so we have
a decoupling of the incentive of each
agent from the well-being of the other
agents in the comments and as a result
because of the interdependency of the
commons we have a decoupling of our own
short-term advantage with our own
long-term well-being if I take the case
of tragedy of the Commons we can see how
recalcitrant and tricky those are if we
take the case of an arms race we see the
same thing and the tricky part here is
we say ok we haven't succeeded with
nuclear deep proliferation all that well
all that we have is more and more
countries having existential level power
so we can't even have something like
mutually assured destruction anymore and
so an obviously exponential tech can
make that non state level actors and not
the increase of all types of dynamics
but now let's take a current example
let's take AI weapons right weaponized
drones etc there is no general in the
world that wants to live in the world
where those weapons are robic waitis yep
there's no military contractor military
Hawk whatever who thinks that's actually
a nicer world to live in everybody
knows that our chance of all being
killed by had drones goes up if any of
us build the things and so it is
a comprehensively worse world for all of
us and our kids and our grandkids and
yeah we're all gonna build the Miss fast
as we can because the other guys
going to build them and we say whoa okay
no no we need to create an agreement
their efforts being made to do this but
all it has to happen is one guy doesn't
one group doesn't join the agreement and
now we don't want them to get the
weaponized drones first so we got to do
it or everybody joins the agreement but
we're pretty sure they're gonna be
defecting on it in secret right because
they would have all of the incentive to
do so so they keep the agreement and
then in a black project they defect on
the agreement while continuing to dis
inform us that they're keeping it and
because we think they're doing that
we're also keeping this inform them
while trying to spy on the way they're
dis informing us and now all of our
resources are going to both making the
world as bad as we can as fast as we can
well dis informing each other and
ruining the information ecology
maximally right we will go extinct
because of multipolar traps on our
current trajectory if we do not figure
out how to solve them these have been
the dynamics that have led to the
collapse of societies for as long as
we've had societies and it's just when
the Roman Empire fell as big as it was
it wasn't the whole world when the Inca
or the Mayan or the Egyptian of the
Mesopotamian and Aztec empire fell which
they all tell it wasn't
everything as soon as we have a fully
interconnected global supply chain where
there's not a country in the world that
could actually build the computer that
we're speaking on from scratch the
mining refinements hardware tech
software tech etcetera is happening
across the whole world then we realize
that the civilization that we only know
how to build civilizations of collapse
and that the collapse of a fully
globalized civilization and where the
environmental damage that's happening is
at the level below biosphere not just a
particular ecosystem you say oh the way
that we have always been multiple our
traps are old we have always been that
has always caused Wars and environmental
destruction and etc is at a level of
magnitude we don't actually get to make
it through so it's not that the problems
are different in kind there's different
in magnet
and speed where that ends up being
different in kind because you don't
actually get to keep going to the
boom-and-bust cycles associated so we
either solve for multipolar traps which
means agency misalignment or the human
experiment completes him yeah yeah yeah
I like I mean I think I real like what
you said they're around I mean like is a
simpler term I wish it were not the case
but I think that you did a good job of
explaining as you said we've only ever
built civilizations that have collapsed
and we live in a world now and and I
think that you're you're correct to say
like we you know we both haven't talked
about the you know distributed
exponential interconnectedness and I
think part of the interconnectedness I
often talk about like the four billion
network smartphones but I think the
global supply chain thing is is is
crucial so as well that everything's
interconnected through the physical
world as well in addition to the
information world and I also like what
you said about decoupling when we think
about these multipolar traps its
decoupling yourself from kind of the
collective in the Commons and then it's
also decoupling your short-term goals
from your long-term goals and then so
that's where cryptocurrency is vibrant
and exciting but it's not without the
share of bad actors exchanges in
personal cows can you hacked computers
can be infected with malware left
unprotected your digital wealth is up
for grabs don't let yourself be a victim
PPE is a safest and simplest way to
protect your Bitcoin ether litecoin and
other tokenized assets this hardware
wallet is a separate device that you
control brought to you by the pioneering
team and shape-shift keep he works with
the wallet software on your computer to
manage your private keys and
transactions
your device has been protected which
provides protection if it falls into the
wrong hands it's large display lets you
carefully view and approve every
transaction and if you keep these ever
lost or stolen you can safely recover
your device without compromising its
private keys the bottom line you'll
sleep easier knowing that your digital
wealth is safe and secure
visit keep key calm to order yours today
and use the code humanist ten for a
limited time 10% discount
so I guess to check on one thing here
though I think and and from me from like
a little bit from an effective alterus
perspective is is when you think about
these kind of I agree that if we don't
solve multipolar traps in these
generator functions of X risk then we
will self terminate I fully agree with
that but the question is at what time
line and so you can imagine a world
where we're trying to solve these kind
of we're at this super abstract kind of
meta level and trying to solve these
kind of generator functions back X risk
Wow oops one of the X risks actually
killed us you know you can also imagine
vice versa where we only solve one of
the X risks but then the generator
functions kill us so how do you think
about kind of the cost of delay there in
terms of like what stuff we should focus
on at which time if you are focusing on
winning at the game that is killing
everything then you are asleep or insane
hi I kind of agree but I bet later let
me pause let me let me let me push back
on that for a second you can imagine a
world in which let's say you and I had
the ability to solve an existential risk
let's say we could press a button and
climate change went away or whatever
that because we or we could concentrate
on solving the generator functions of X
risk I could see some versions and work
on that for like a longer time whatever
I could see a version of reality where
we were certain people try to solve the
the X risk itself rather than the kind
of meta level generator functions
we have to be focused on the generator
functions because otherwise not only if
we try and solve for a specific extras
that is a result of the underlying
system architectures and dynamics that
made that risk and lots of risks like it
not only do we not solve the other cases
but there is a decent chance that as
we've mentioned about goals before we
actually solve it in a way that makes
something else more likely and and this
is why so when I said if we are trying
to win at the game that is killing
everything basically whenever I've all
this games and we're a sleeper in same
thing we just either don't understand
the phenomena or there or something else
wrong then what we also realize is that
trying to just keep addressing the
symptoms without addressing what's
causing them doesn't make any sense
either and so then we have to say okay
well at minimum I want to focus on one
if I don't know how to solve
the underlying generator functions I at
least want to make sure that the actions
that I'm doing to the degree that they
are successful create precedence where
if more people do them the system at
least moves in the right direction it's
a race to the top rather than the race
to the bottom at least want to make sure
I'm doing that
meaning I'm creating dynamics where my
ability to win is through better
partnership rather than better rivalry
rather than the example where I figure
out that if I get the you know if I
figure out how to factory it eyes farms
I can produce more meat per dollar and
have higher margins on my need moving
towards ubiquitous factory farming that
is just ruinous for everything that's
been a multipolar trap race to the
bottom the kind of free-range organic
movement that is saying no people will
actually pay more for the thing that is
healthier and better for them that also
happens to be better for the world and
less ethically terrible let's do
something where to the degree we
succeeded this and other people follow
the system dynamics are better
that doesn't categorically solve for the
issue of multipolar trap but it at least
says within the kinds of systems we
understand like capitalism we're going
to move system dynamics in the right
direction so one of the things people
want to really focus on is is the source
of differential value that they're able
to provide within any project within
capitalism something that to the degree
that it's successful and other people
try to replicate it create system
dynamics that move in the right
direction versus wrong direction
absolutely one way that people can think
about within the current systems how to
be in the right direction some people
will be focused on how do we actually
solve the underlying generator functions
and we spoke about the generator
function from one perspective which is
that rival risk dynamics cause harm and
the exponential rivalry causing
exponential harm self terminates yep
there is another way of speaking about
the generator function that is even more
fundamental and abstract and I think it
would be worth sharing that if because
it speaks to what we have to change if
your app let's yeah so then actually I
was about to go there cuz I try we're
essentially we're we're operating at the
level of what I would call meta X risk
the generator functions of X risk we
pushed down for a bit there to the
actual s X risks themselves and now
let's go actually from one level of
abstraction further up so tell me yeah
what is the thing that
is actually one level above these
generator functions of X racing yeah so
the one generator function we've talked
about rival resetting image we got that
I want to give one other example of a
generator function and then we'll go to
an even more abstract unifying framework
when you mention hey let's say we solve
climate change is that adequate and is
it even an appropriate thing to do so so
let's take an example where we're not
focused on like increasing war through
exponential tech weaponization or
whatever but we'll focused on simply
environmental collapse dynamics so when
we look at environmental damage dynamics
all the environmental damage that we
look at can be thought of in terms of
either depletion of under noble
resources or accumulation of waste
streams that aren't being processed in
real time and so accumulation and
depletion when we start to look at the
example so I say okay accumulation right
what we call toxicity whether I'm
talking about nitrogen runoff causing
dead zones or the plastic in the ocean
or mercury in the water or in the air or
uranium or carbon dioxide causing
carbonic acid in ocean acidification or
carbon dioxide in the air or any of
those right the the CFCs are HFCS that
were the ozone hole problem those are
all special case examples of some kind
of accumulation of something that
doesn't have a feedback loop that can
process it in real time that has some
externalize costs on the the
antifragility of the ecosystem writ
large if I try and focus on one of them
and say hey I'm just going to sequester
a bunch of co2 but I'm not stopping the
nitrogen runoff or the you know any of
those other ones the biodiversity loss
or whatever then what we'll find as I
move the curve a tiny bit but I haven't
addressed the fact that there are many
many different metrics that are all
moving to collapse from the same
underlying dynamic similarly on the
other side of depletion whether them
talking about cutting down the
old-growth forests or overfishing the
ocean or species extinction of
biodiversity loss or peak nitrogen
turkey
for us or any of those things those are
all examples simile of unremovable
resource utilization and an exponential
curve on how that is happening so then
we say let's put those both together and
we look at that in a natural ecosystem
like a forest there is no Unruh knowable
use of resource and there is no
accumulated waste every new thing is
made from old things all the old things
get turned into new things so you have
comprehensive loop closure all the atoms
are in closed loop atomic cycling so
that the atoms from one thing when it
dies become new things at the same speed
that things are dying that or train ways
the antifragility of nature is a
function of a few things but primarily
for this example a function of closed
loop dynamics the fragility of the human
bill world is largely a function of open
loop dynamics so when we look at
depletion on one side and accumulation
on the other those are the two sides of
a linear atomic economy or materials
resource economy that we can say the
underlying dynamic of linear flows
rather than closed loop cycles or open
loops and a network diagram is the way
we define toxicity we're at large then
we need to work on the generator
function not of just this one specific
accumulation or depletion issue but how
do we have a process by which
comprehensive loop closure is built into
the choice making processes of all
humans everywhere yep and as soon as we
start thinking about it that way not
just like how could we do it somewhere
but how do we create a different type of
behavioral dynamics from incentive
structures to collective intelligence
structures are basically the sense
making and choice making dynamics that
lead to all agents thinking about and
working towards comprehensive loop
closure that is now at a meta level to
all of the specific instantiations so
now we go one level deeper and we say we
talked about rival risk dynamics
multiplied by exponential tech self
terminates we also talked about linear
flows open loop flows on a finite planet
also in the bleeding
dynamic there is something that unifies
both of those so we can flip them meta
meta ex risk yep and we noticed that
both of these involve specifically human
and human choice empowered by technology
in relationship with some kind of world
or Commons right and so if I look at
rival risk dynamics if there wasn't
exponential tech if we stayed with stone
tools we wouldn't really have any risk
of self induced extinction we would just
keep killing each other but we wouldn't
kill everybody we couldn't have a war
that killed everybody and we wouldn't be
able to cut down all the treats right
and so specifically it requires not just
tech but ever-growing tech right tech
feedback curves and similarly if our
tools were limited to a size where like
say we have just fishing lines not
mile-long drift nets we wouldn't fish
all the fish out of the ocean
but as soon as we've got mile-long drift
nets and we've got D nines taking down
forests and slash-and-burn whatever else
then again we start to see these
fragility dynamics get larger than the
playing field can handle because you've
got movements that are faster than the
antifragility can process now we say why
is that and here's the key insight for
all the people that are thinking about
how can we use the technology to make
the world better and use technology in a
fundamentally evolutionary way and the
fact that people might say well look
nature's rival risks and so we take
market dynamics as kind of an example of
a social darwinism of looking at how
nature works and applying it to
ourselves and am I talking about
something that sounds like it is not how
nature works well kind of yes and no and
but there's this is really really
critical because this is one place where
people think they're thinking through
formal systems but they're the wrong
formal systems in nature pre humans
let's say pre Homo habilis in the
development of evolving technology or
developing technology we see micro
rivalry
meaning this lion and this gazelle
obviously in the moment of the chase
have a rival risk relationship with each
other the lion wants what the gazelle
doesn't wanna be the lion doesn't want
and they're kind of mutually exclusive
so cool we we have a rival risk dynamic
they're at a micro level and yet
gazelles as a whole species and lions as
a whole species depend upon each other
and if they if either one died the other
one would probably go extinct and so
then we say how is it that in nature
micro local rivalry leads to macro
symbiosis and interdependence and is it
the same in humans or not because
obviously social Darwinism and lazier
capitalism says yes it is the same
compete and the best happens and we
innovate and those who produce the best
goods and services and the best values
and proliferate and have the most money
because money is a concentrated form of
choice making but they they did the good
things with joy so they should have more
choice name ID that's the idea right and
it is gibberish and it's important to
understand really critically why it's
gibberish as soon as we developed
technology and I'm going to define what
I mean by this very specifically in a
moment we change the fundamental system
dynamics and the same system dynamics do
not and can not apply so let's go to a
chimpanzee who obviously uses tools or a
bird with a nest or a beaver or whatever
right like they are tool users if I give
a chimpanzee or if a chimpanzee just
finds on its own a rock and it wants to
cut some vine and it just starts rubbing
the rock across the vine it
experientially notices how good this
particular rock is at cutting it has a
eminent experience of that if it picks
up another rock and they experience it
cutting faster they will use the sharper
rock if you give them a knife they will
experience a cutting posture and they
will use the knife but they have never
invented knives and there's a reason is
that our current standard narrative said
this start with Homo habilis this kind
of tool evolving capacity rather than
just tool using capacity so let's take
that so it requires the
city for abstraction which developed
along with prefrontal cortex etc to be
able to use this rock and fill the
sharpness in this rock and fill
sharpness this rock filler sharpness and
understand something that is none of the
rocks which is the abstract principle of
sharpness what makes something sharp and
how could I make something that is more
sharp now I'm not focused on the
instance of any of the rocks but a
principle that they all have in common
but that is none of them that
abstraction capacity seems to have
emerged with some earlier hominid and
then have Zenith tin Homo sapiens and
that allows us to say well I would try
chipping it with a and to make an
arrowhead and then I would make a knife
and then I would make a laser right I
can keep doubling down on the abstract
principle of sharpness I get evolving
tech and this is why beavers are kind of
doing the same thing they were doing a
long time ago with regard to tools it
was part of an evolved dynamic and we
are changing our entire environment one
generation to the next so radically now
why does this matter
evolution and I know this is a bit of a
long one but this is because this is
actually the heart of the whole
thing so thank you for indulging me
evolution is a kind of creative process
meaning it is a process by which new
stuff comes to exist that didn't exist
before and when we think about what the
process of evolution is we have some
kind of mutation and some kind of
selection dynamics right so there is a
distribution of things that are pretty
similar but a little bit different and
then the ones that are a little bit
different in a slightly more adaptive
way in the moment meaning can either
survive or make better end up having a
better chance of making it through
whatever characteristics led to doing
that get double down on etc so what we
find is that that process happens
extraordinarily slowly not by design
it's an unconscious process right
there's an unconscious process of
mutation and an unconscious process of
selection nobody is saying this one
seems like a more truly and beautiful
approach let's go with it this seems
like a good future into perpetuity it's
just these guys actually got food better
or made it better and that's what gets
elected for
which can include selecting for things
that move in the direction of increasing
violence dominance capacity whatever but
at least in nature one of the things
that happens is that the rival risk
dynamics where power is used in a
rivalry sway in a micro context there is
a coupling of there's a symmetrical
coupling of the rates of power change so
as a lion as lions are evolving to get
to be better hunters over the course of
hundreds or thousands of generations
gazelles are also evolving to get faster
because the gazelles that make it
through are better getting away from the
Lions and the lines that make it better
getting the zealots right into there and
their reproduction times are similar
enough and they their system dynamics
are embedded in or related so you don't
get a symmetries of power you actually
have a radical binding of power symmetry
from lion - lion and from gazelle to
gazelle and from lion to gazelle and
from gazelle to plant and the whole
thing right now this is key this is
actually the essential criteria that
makes micro rivalry lead to macro
symbiosis is the symmetrical power
binding imagine for a moment that I
could make a mutation where Lions got a
hundred times better at killing in one
generation well in that one generation
they would kill all the gazelles they'd
eat them all and then they would go
extinct and so what we would find is
that those species that were so much
more effective than their environment
could actually navigate in that crate
resilience - would self terminate
because of their own effectiveness in
dependent upon of the ecological niche
they depend upon they would be debasing
the substrate upon which they depend
through their over over expression and
we see this virus happens virus comes
about it is so lethal that it kills the
host before it gets to I'm actually
propagate and then less virulent
versions of that virus get to propagate
more and nature actions of selecting for
a virus that's moving more in the
direction of symbiosis than just
lethality right yes yeah and so
evolution itself has this symmetrical
power binding why this is so
critical to understand is because
nature does not select for individuals
of a species and it doesn't even select
for species it seems to over the very
short term but as you zoom out over the
long term it selects for
self-stabilizing ecological niches where
the particulars members of a species
that seem like they're getting selected
for over the short term that are super
lethal over the long term self-terminate
and so the things that make it through
long term are these radically anti
fragile symbiotic systems and so we said
so okay we get that in nature and we we
look at the most badass apex predators
in nature whether we're looking at a
lion or a shark or whatever and we look
at a lion killing a gazelle compared to
what a human factory farm of cows looks
like right and we look at a shark eating
a tuna compared to a mile long drift
more if a mile long like if
great whites got mile-long drift nets
the whole ocean would have not existed a
long time ago and so as soon as we
developed technology and the ability to
double down on technology we broke the
power symmetry and we have to think
about two applications humans with
regard to other humans and humans with
regard to the rest of nature that they
depend upon so humans with regard to
other humans the most powerful lion is
not that much most powerful than then
more powerful than the next most
powerful lion and it's not even that
much more powerful than the average lion
or even one of the weaker lions if you
think about it like the most powerful
lion is maybe 1.1 or 1.2 X more powerful
than that the upper incoming lion who
will overtake him soon now look at human
power distributions and say how much
more destructive power does a Putin or a
Trump have than you do a lot more
dangerous crazy yeah like the ability to
destroy the whole planet versus the
ability to like maybe hit somebody right
and maybe you can get a gun right and
you look at here okay I don't know is
that nine is that
there's a magnitude it's a lot okay well
that's a huge power asymmetry
now humans with regard to nature we can
cut down the forest much much much
faster than forces forest can replenish
we can use up resources faster than they
can replenish we can create toxicity
first link and replenish etc as a result
that's why the ohm den loop dynamics
matter so much is because nature cannot
actually process the speed of
transitions that we are making right and
because we are increasing our predatory
capacity faster than the environment can
evolve because the technology is a
second creative process what we would
call design is not design is a
consciously mediated abstraction
oriented process evolution is an
unconsciously mediated non abstract
eminent kind of process evolution leads
to radical interdependent complexities
technology allows the selection over the
short term of something that has
independent of its relationship with the
rest of the whole and so if we as soon
as we get that those are mathematically
fundamentally different design gives us
complicated systems that are all fragile
you notice everything that humans build
the house that I'm in can't repair
itself the way that a fight that have
forced what if a fire took in the
computer I'm on doesn't repair itself
knowing my body does so design gives us
a finite number of parameters that we
can then externally build something for
right complicated systems but very very
powerful complexity antifragility
happens by self-organization we don't
really know how to do that but we do
know how to debase it we know how to
have the complicated debase the complex
substrate upon which it depends that's
how we get increasing fragility as we
have collapse so why this matters is
technology itself is a fundamentally new
creative process in the history of local
universe it breaks the power symmetry
and as a result it makes micro rivalry
turn into macro rivalry rather than
micro rivalry turn into macro symbiosis
as a result rather than get increasing
antifragility we get increasing
fragility towards inevitable collapse
dynamics and so what that means is the
relationship between the creative
process called technology creating
complicated systems and the relationship
between the evolutionary creative
process creating complex systems the
relationship between those is the thing
that we actually have to change and
modulate because we still have rival
risk basis for choice humans choosing
against each other in a reverse way that
came from evolution but now extended
through design technology complicated
systems the our understanding of causal
principles optimization in a way where
the rival risk dynamics are no longer
checked in a way that creates any
balance so what we actually need is a
new creative process a new process by
which new stuff comes into existence
that is neither evolution nor design it
is a third thing or not designing parts
to we're not designing individual pieces
of technology that empower rival risk
choice-making basis we are and we're not
waiting for anti rivalry at a macro
level through evolutionary process we
are actually designing self-stabilizing
complex ecological niches and designing
in the relationship between the
complicated and the complex to be itself
metastable that what we would call
evolution by design or you know
sometimes referred to as transcendental
design is a actual different
mathematical process of new stuff coming
into being than either evolution or
designers and we can see that at the
heart of it design is all about the
understanding of causation we can
understand the law we can understand how
a causal dynamic works you can make a
tool that allows us to manipulate that
law right so science is the
understanding of causation and then
technology is the application of it to
have more effective causation to be able
to cause stuff at larger scale but our
basis for choice science
and give us a good basis for choice
because its first person in science
studies third person which is why it
said we say what is not what on our
basis for choice is still coming from
social Darwinism so coming from a
rivalries evolutionary basis those two
together is an unstable system heading
towards collapse we actually need it in
a theory of choice beyond games theory
beyond social Darwinism that can be an
adequate container for our causal
dynamics and to be able to actually hold
the relationship between choice and
causation appropriate to have
metastability that is if you want to
talk about the macro level of the
generator functions of X risk it is the
relationship between choice and
causation within the field of change and
the necessity for a theory of and
systems of right choice making at the
level of individuals and collectives
that can steward the level of causal
power that we have through technology in
ways that will create systems that are
actually anti fragile and meta State mmm
it thank you for the conclusion there
and let's just for the listeners and
this is gonna be I'm just gonna wrap up
and then we'll kind of transition to a
full wrap-up mode but as you said there
first we have we've already been talking
about - did the generator functions of s
extra store one of them as the and rival
risk
games with distributed exponential
technology with interconnectedness leads
to self-determination and you can think
about the loop closures as another part
of this where you have from a stock and
flow perspective you have depletion or
accumulation of various things and when
those go to zero or in those two go to
infinity that's also really bad for us
so those two things our generator
functions about extras but in fact as
you're saying here there's one kind of
one meta level above that which is to
say that both of those things are the
result of this new kind of process new
technological process and that process
is different than the evolutionary
process and evolutionary process as you
said is really good at taking if you
think from a multi scale perspective
it's really good at taking the micro
rivalry and trends you know transforming
it into macro you know symbiosis or anti
fragility but technology does not do
that technology does not have that micro
to macro kind of thing and so we need to
do is kind of think about the
relationship between these two processes
we've created a new process aka
technology and we've had this whole
process
aka evolution we have to think
what is the relationship between those
things and how can we make a third kind
of process that as you say is something
kind of a combination of them that
allows us to do the self designed
bottom-up anti fragile creation
so with that Daniel I know we're out of
time here um and just for our listeners
too as a quick note a you can go check
out some of Daniels work at civilization
emerging calm and I'd recommend that
because lots of the ideas here are there
the other thing to note is that likely
this will not be the last podcast
between Daniel and I because you know he
left it at a very juicy edge there which
is what is the life we have science as
their theory of kind of truth or
whatever the world what is our theory of
ethics in the world was there processed
for that we need to dive into that we
need to dive into how this relates to
our current information revolution how
this relates to black swans and the
precautionary principle in progress and
also what you as a person can do about
all this uh-huh so well there'll be
another one likely but Dana was there
anything else that you would like to say
to our listeners either a place that
they can find you on the interwebs or or
in the last thought that was a very
concise and valuable wrap-up I
appreciate it and yeah I'm very happy to
come back and take the next step because
as you said we shared some frameworks
without actually sharing the rest of the
frameworks necessary to understand it or
how to act with those frameworks so I'm
happy to come back and do that you
already shared my blog so these topics
are interesting to people I look forward
to hearing questions thoughts that come
up